Finding Aid for Barbara Bach papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Barbara Bach papers 1960-2008, 1975-2007
Bach, Barbara.
(in 10 boxes)
9.3 linear feet
2013048 Aa 2
Barbara Bach first worked as a Boston area schoolteacher and creator of television documentaries. After receiving a Master's degree in Education in 1969, she became an Ann Arbor, Mich. businesswoman, networking facilitator, fundraiser, and lifelong educator/mentor to individuals and organizations. The collection includes business records, association newsletters, campaign literature, photographs, and correspondence representing her multiple careers as an entrepreneur, legislative aide, community activist, and executive director in a policy environment promoting economic development in Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Barbara Bach (donor no. 10556 ) in 2011.
Further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Barbara Bach graduated from Vassar College in 1956, then completed additional post-graduate coursework at Harvard University. After college, she got married, changed her last name to Damon, and became an elementary school teacher. Bach was an active member of the Greater Boston Area Junior League and, in an era when few career options were available to women, she produced two documentary programs on special education topics for public television station WGBH-TV, Boston, Massachusetts.
By the fall of 1968, when she moved to Ann Arbor to complete her Master's degree in Education from the University of Michigan, she was a single parent with two young children as well as herself to support. After graduating in 1969, she worked as a teacher, tutor, and educational consultant for several years. She also became active in local politics and the Ann Arbor Democratic Party, serving as its chairperson from 1980-1982.
During the mid-1970s, she was married to Samuel J. Eldersveld, Professor of Political Science at the University of Michigan and former Democratic Mayor of Ann Arbor, 1957-1959. She remained Barbara Eldersveld until re-adopting her maiden name, Barbara Bach, in 1992.
In 1977, perhaps inspired by a Women's Conference she attended in Houston, Texas that year, Barbara Bach and a group of Ann Arbor women became entrepreneurs. She was one of five original co-owners of the Moveable Feast, an Ann Arbor restaurant and catering business that continued to grow in popularity after she sold her share of the business in 1979 to the other partners.
From 1979 to 1983, she worked as a legislative aide to Perry Bullard, then the State Representative from Ann Arbor. Bach's personal lobbying efforts and her persuasive writing skills helped to win passage of Bullard's legislative initiatives, including the bill he introduced to boycott South Africa in protest of that nation's apartheid policy.
From April 1983 through August 1984, Bach directed a Lansing-based public service organization called the Michigan Tax Information Council, employing her communication skills there in a monthly newsletter intended to educate citizens of the state about tax policy.
In 1984, Bach accepted a new position as Director, Economic Development and Job Training (ED & JT) Network, Michigan Community Colleges. In this role she acted as a liaison among the presidents of 29 Michigan Community Colleges. She herself also completed state-supported training and became a certified Small Business Development Counselor. In 1985, the role of the ED and JT Network became a more formalized focus of the Lansing-based Michigan Community Colleges Association (MCCA) and by 1986 the MCCA had absorbed the ED and JT Network.
Bach also applied her expertise in bringing people together around an educational goal through occasional employment as a program consultant to the University of Michigan (UM), the city of Ann Arbor, and Washtenaw County, and as a visiting lecturer at Eastern Michigan University (EMU). In 1987, as a consultant with the UM Industrial Development Division (IDD), she completed a pilot project on "Establishing an Invention Evaluation and Inventor Assistance Program...".
In June of 1989, she was offered and accepted a position in Ann Arbor as Executive Director of the Inventors' Council of Michigan (INCOM). At the time, INCOM provided education and networking opportunities for 'inventors,' in the broader sense of 'product developers.' According to its July 1988 Business Plan, INCOM had been operated since 1983 by the University of Michigan Industrial Development Division and was now proposing "to expand its membership to include service providers, corporations, and government sectors concerned with economic development in Michigan."
Bach had worked with INCOM to facilitate its 1987 organizational transition from UM support to private sector support through grants and membership fees. Ed Zimmer, a local entrepreneur, and the Zimmer Foundation provided early support to INCOM then redirected their efforts to focus on an Inventor/Entrepreneur Network Newsletter. As INCOM's new Executive Director, in 1990 Bach helped to negotiate INCOM's organizational affiliation with Detroit's Metropolitan Center for High Technology (MCHT).
However, funding became increasingly scarce and INCOM's affiliation with MCHT ceased as of January 1992. For a time, Bach and other volunteer board and advisory committee members continued to direct INCOM operations but, without consistent funding, INCOM's volunteer board members eventually left to pursue other interests. Some of INCOM's original goals and activities continue to be represented through the monthly meetings of the New Enterprise Forum (NEF), an informal network with a somewhat narrower focus begun in 1986.
Throughout the 1990s and the first decade of the new millennium, Barbara Bach also contributed her energy and expertise to a wide range of Ann Arbor community service activities and advisory boards.
The Barbara Bach papers reflect a context of turbulent economic conditions and ground-breaking socio-political events. Some defining highlights of Bach's political efforts include her work with the Ann Arbor Public Schools Title IX Monitoring Committee for gender equality in sports, her nonpartisan campaign work for the county-wide Washtenaw County SAFE House proposal to assist victims of domestic violence, and her Democratic Party campaign work on behalf of Albert H. Wheeler, Ann Arbor's first African American mayor.
However, Bach's business experience and activities on behalf of economic development and job training in the State of Michigan, in connection with the Michigan Community Colleges Association (MCCA) and as Executive Director of the Inventors' Council of Michigan (INCOM), represent the bulk of the collection.
During the 1980s, community colleges were becoming a focal point for job-related training as a precursor to economic development. Organizations such as the Michigan Technology Council (MTC), with support from the University of Michigan, brought together leaders from business, industry, and government in an effort to facilitate technology transfer through commercial applications and new product development.
Economic recession had helped to heighten interest, at all levels of government, in the policy concept of economic development through entrepreneurial successes. Ideally, through teaching, research, and networking assistance, an entrepreneurial "supercenter" would encourage new product and business development, ultimately creating jobs throughout the economy.
Throughout much of her career in Michigan, Barbara Bach was known as Barbara Eldersveld. The collection also includes some materials from her early public service activities in Massachusetts as Barbara Damon.
The collection is organized into eight series: Personal/Biographical, Greater Boston Area, Teaching and Educational Settings, Political, Business and Entrepreneurial, State Government, Inventors' Council of Michigan (INCOM), and Ann Arbor Community Service.
Subjects:
Bach, Barbara.; Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.; Inventors Council of Michigan.; Michigan Community College Association.; Michigan Technology Council.; Businesswomen--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Community colleges--Michigan.; Fund raisers (Persons)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical 1968-2001
  The Personal/Biographical series, 1968-2001 (0.3 linear ft.), contains material relating to Bach's developmental psychology studies, school research project, and other personal history, including professional photographs. Several versions of resumes created throughout her career are included, and job search correspondence. This series also includes a booklet commemorating the 35th reunion of her Vassar College cohort.
  - Graduate School at University of Michigan 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Developmental Psychology Seminar 1974 (Box 1)
  - School Research Study
    - Bibliography and notes 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Report: "Attitudes toward school...school structure," June 1974 (Box 1)
    - Communications 1974 (Box 1)
  - Law School Application Essay 1976 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Civil Service Application 1986 (Box 1)
  - Aptitude Assessment and Myers Briggs Type Indicator, ca 1987 (Box 1)
  - Certificates, Publicity, Awards 1985, 1986, 1990, 1993, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1984, 1989, 1990 undated (Box 1)
  - Resumes
    - General Format 1966-1982 (Box 1)
    - Consulting/Business Planning (w/ photo business card) 1986-1990 (Box 1)
    - Public Relations and Policy Development 1982-1992 (Box 1)
    - Candidate for City Council 1995 (Box 1)
  - Job Search Correspondence
    - 1968, 1974-1976, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1983, 1986, 1987 (Box 1)
    - United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit 1983 (Box 1)
  - Vassar College, 35th Reunion 1991 (Box 1)
  - Week at Findhorn, Scotland 1993 (Box 1)
  - Housing Bureau for Seniors Home Share Program 1993, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Inspiration for Working Women
    - Articles, Guides 1969-1997 (Box 1)
    - Cartoons, Humor, Events, Art 1979-2001 (Box 1)
- Greater Boston Area 1960-1967
  The Greater Boston Area series, 1960-1967 (0.1 linear ft.), contains research notes, recommendations, and scripts related to the two public television documentaries she produced. The series also includes some correspondence pertaining to her Junior League of Boston and other volunteer activities.
  - Correspondence 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Documentary Programs for WGBH-TV Channel 2
    - Research and Volunteers 1960 (Box 1)
    - Recommendations and Script 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Junior League of Boston Correspondence 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Other Volunteer Activities 1967 (Box 1)
- Teaching and Educational Settings 1969-1986
  The Teaching and Educational Settings series, 1969-1986 (0.2 linear ft.), contains memos, meeting minutes, and articles related to Bach's role in the Ann Arbor Public Schools Title IX program implementation and monitoring committee. The folder representing a University of Michigan School of Education program for educational opportunity includes a bibliography compiled by Bach on equal educational opportunity in high school athletics. Records from Bach's participation in Eastern Michigan University's student teaching program are also included, and job search correspondence.
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools
    - 1973-1978 (Box 1)
    - Title IX
      - Implementation 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - Monitoring Committee 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Athletics Task Force 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Eastern Michigan University 1970, 1977-1978, 1985 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Employment Applications 1975, 1976, 1978-1979, 1986 (Box 1)
    - School of Education Program for Educational Opportunity 1975 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Community College 1983-1984, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Wellesley College, Washington Internship Program Application 1969 (Box 1)
  - Other 1975, 1986 (Box 1)
- Political 1997-2005
  The Political series, 1972-2005 (bulk 1975-1996, 1 linear ft.), contains newspaper clippings and campaign materials, including photographs, documenting Bach's role in Al Wheeler's Ann Arbor mayoral campaigns, Ed Pierce's congressional campaign, and the campaigns of several other candidates. Campaign literature for Bach's own candidacy for Ann Arbor City Council representative is also included, and news coverage of her general assistance in Ann Arbor City Elections. The series also documents Ann Arbor Democratic Party membership and fundraising activities from 1980 to 1983. Finally, it also contains correspondence, press releases, reports, and other materials related to Bach's role as a legislative aide to State Representative Perry Bullard.
  - Candidate for Barton Hills Village Trustee 1973 (Box 1)
  - Al Wheeler Mayoral Campaigns
    - 1975
      - Literature and Call List (Box 1)
      - Photographs (Box 1)
    - April 4th 1977 (Box 1)
    - Rematch, April 3rd (includes misc. candidate photographs) 1978 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Democratic Party (Chair 1980-1982)
    - Membership and Fundraising 1976, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
      (scattered dates)
    - Re-apportionment Committee 1981 (Box 1)
    - Winter Warming 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor News Election Night Photo and Editorial 1986 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Democratic Women's Club 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Ed Pierce Congressional Campaign 1976 (Box 1)
    (includes one photograph)
  - Editor of:
    - Ann Arbor Democrat, September Issue, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Democrat, September 1977 through June 1979 (Box 1)
    - Washtenaw County Democrat, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Marjorie Lansing Congressional Campaign 1974 (Box 1)
  - National Women's Conference, Houston Texas 1977 (Box 1)
  - Other Campaigns
    - Miscellaneous Candidates and Offices 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      (includes Philip Power photo, letter from Perry Bullard)
    - James Kenworthy for Mayor 1979 (Box 1)
      (includes photos)
    - Perkins for Council 1980 (Box 1)
    - Brater for Mayor, Pollard for Judge 1991, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Alma Wheeler Smith for State Senate 1994 (Box 1)
    - Lana Pollack for United States Senate 1994 (Box 1)
    - Pam Byrnes for State Representative 2005 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Aide to State Representative Bullard (Box 2)
    - Correspondence Received 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - Art Bills: Public Act 474, 475 of 1980 Support Letters 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Art Dealer Bills of 1982 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Constituent Information/Freedom of Information Act and Legislative Process 1979, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Legislative Efforts and Correspondence 1979-1982 (Box 2)
    - Candidate for Congress 1982 (Box 2)
    - South Africa Legislation
      - Correspondence 1980-1983 (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan Divestment 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - Press Releases 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - Published Summary, ca 1985 (Box 2)
      - Voting Support 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Sound Recording of Divestment Hearing, House Bill 4838, 1980, Audio-cassette tape (Box 10)
    - Bach Writing Samples 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Women-focused Events
      - "Take Back the Night," 1981 and Correspondence, 1972-1981 (Box 10)
      - "Women's Speak-Out" at Washtenaw Community College 1981 (Box 10)
    - Washtenaw County Women's Economic Agenda 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    - Washtenaw County Economic Development Partnership Report 1982 (Box 10)
  - City of Ann Arbor
    - Second Ward Vacancy (February), Newspaper Clippings 1993 (Box 10)
    - Elections (April), Additional Newspaper Clippings 1993 (Box 10)
    - City Council Campaign
      - Continue as Second Ward Representative 1993 (Box 10)
      - Seek Election to return to Council (2nd Ward) 1995 (Box 10)
      - Nominating Petitions and Resume 1995 (Box 10)
      - Ann Arbor Area Quality Indicators Project 1995 (Box 10)
      - University of Michigan, Student Assembly Proposal, "Blurring the Town and Gown," 1995 (Box 10)
    - Elections (November), Newspaper Coverage 1996 (Box 10)
- Business and Entrepreneurial 1977-1993
  The Business and Entrepreneurial series, 1977-1992 (1.5 linear ft.), contains sample menus and memorabilia from the Moveable Feast as well as samples of its financial records. Much of the material relating to the Michigan Technology Council (MTC) and Michigan Community Colleges (MCC) is in the form of business communications, including reports and meeting agendas as well as correspondence. Since Eldersveld's initial position with the MCC Association (MCCA) involved working as a liaison between the presidents of member community colleges and local businesses, materials from this segment of her work with the MCCA's Economic Development and Job Training (ED&JT) Network are included here in the Business and Entrepreneurial series.
  - The Moveable Feast
    - Business Prospectus and Idea Articles 1977, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Financial Planning and Administration 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Legal 1977 (Box 10)
    - Logo and Memorabilia 1977, 1979, 1989, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Management Decisions 1978-1979 (Box 10)
    - Menus 1973, 1976, 1977-1978 (Box 10)
    - Opening Day Guests, Signs, Early Menus and Prices 1977 (Box 10)
    - Photos and Photographic Slides, ca 1977 (Box 10)
    - "Soundings" and Career Options 1978 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Technology Council (MTC)
    - Economic Development Education
      - Proposal for Center 1982 (Box 10)
      - Ann Arbor Entrepreneurial Center 1983 (Box 10)
    - Announcement of New Leadership, "Opportunity" Letters 1993 (Box 10)
    - Job Fair and Executive Director Search 1984, 1986 (Box 10)
    - Newsletter Michigan Technology Update
      - September, October, December, January, March, June, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
      - January, April, May, 1992 Membership Information, 1992, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Science and Technology Quest 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - Michigan's Leading Edge Technologies Award Entry Form 1992 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Community Colleges (MCC)
    - Views on Assessing Effectiveness of Economic Programs/Job Training 1984-1987 (Box 10)
    - Concept of "An Entrepreneurial Supercenter," 1984 (Box 10)
    - Department of Labor Report on Employee Ownership Interest 1985 (Box 10)
    - Business Climate and Technology
      - American Enterprise Institute, Argoff Paper on New Technology and Education (e.g., MI Industrial Technology Inst.) 1984 (Box 10)
      - Women in Business 1983, 1985, 1986 (Box 10)
      - United Auto Workers (UAW)-Ford Employee Development and Training Program 1984 (Box 10)
      - Entrepreneurship in Corporations and Venture Capital in Michigan 1985 (Box 10)
      - National Community College Month, Journal 1986 (Box 10)
      - Newsletters and Studies 1986-1987 (Box 10)
      - North Force Magazine supplement, West Central Michigan Community Growth Alliance (CGA), 1989 (Box 10)
    - State of Michigan Projects
      - Board of Education Status Study Report 1982 (Box 10)
      - Michigan Occupational Deans Administrative Council (MODAC), Mazarra Proposal 1982 (Box 10)
      - Human Investment Project 1985 (Box 10)
      - Department of Education Grant-Networking Concept 1984-1985 (Box 10)
    - Economic Development and Job Training (ED&JT) Network (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Director Position 1984 (Box 3)
      - Community Colleges and Workforce Development 1984-1986 (Box 3)
      - MCC Community Services Association (CSA) 1984, 1985, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Plans for 1984-1985 (CSA Institutional Model), 1984 (Box 3)
      - Network Activities and Administrative Affiliates 1984 (Box 3)
      - Network News (Newsletter)
        - 1982-1984 (Box 3)
        - 1985 (Box 3)
        - 1986 (Box 3)
      - Annual Report 1985 (Box 3)
      - Purpose of the Network/Objectives 1985 (Box 3)
      - Executive Leadership Workshop/John Porter Address 1985 (Box 3)
      - Conferences
        - The Entrepreneurship Institute/Zupnick, President 1984 (Box 3)
        - Entrepreneurs/Intellectual Property 1985 (Box 3)
        - Spring/Midland MI-JTPA (Job Training Partnership Act), Community Growth Alliance (CGA) Targets 1985 (Box 3)
        - Follow-up on "Demand-Driven" Job Training/P. Power 1985 (Box 3)
        - Spring/Muskegon MI, "Serving Business and Industry," 1986 (Box 3)
        - November "Drive-In" on Institutionalizing Economic Development 1985 (Box 3)
        - Northwestern Michigan College, "Trends in Occupational Studies," 1986 (Box 3)
      - Lippitt Proposal on Community College Partnership with Business 1984 (Box 3)
      - Surveys of Programs for Small Business Development 1983 (Box 3)
      - Daily Newspapers in Michigan 1984 (Box 3)
      - Job Training Program (Quickstart)/ Training Projects 1983-1985 (Box 3)
      - Job Forecasting Profile Proposal 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - List of Ann Arbor Area Employers, ca 1985 (Box 3)
      - Handbook on Job Training and Economic Development 1985 (Box 3)
      - Small Business Education Program 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Entrepreneurial Education Proposal 1985 (Box 3)
      - Proposal-Michigan Department of Education Grant 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - Rating Sheets for 1985-1986 Network Proposal, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Technology Transfer
        - Task Force 1985 (Box 3)
        - Delivery System Concept Paper (January) 1985 (Box 3)
        - Center at Michigan State University (MSU), ca 1986 (Box 3)
      - MCC Presidents' ED&JT Committee
        - Meeting Agenda and Notes 1982 (Box 3)
        - Network Project for 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Presidential Leadership ad hoc Committee 1985 (Box 3)
      - Presidents' November Meeting 1985 (Box 3)
      - Steering Committee
        - Job Training and Retraining Investment Fund
          - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
          - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
        - Plans for 1985-1986 Network Directions, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
        - Overview 1986 (Box 3)
      - Bay de Noc Community College, Administrative Organization Chart and Job Descriptions 1984 (Box 3)
      - Organization Structure and Relationship to Michigan Community Colleges Association (MCCA) 1985 (Box 3)
    - Governor's Task Force/Entrepreneurial Education, Eastern Michigan University (EMU) Proposal 1985 (Box 3)
    - Eastern Michigan University, Institute for Community and Regional Development (ICARD) Newsletters 1989, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Ferris State College, Center for Occupational Education 1985 (Box 3)
    - Kirkland Community College, "Small Business Triad" and W. K. Kellogg Foundation 1986 (Box 3)
    - Lake Michigan College, Practitioners' Academy Proposal 1986 (Box 3)
    - Lansing Community College, "Where Futures Begin," ca 1985 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University Workshop on Michigan Choices 1985 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan (UM)
      - College of Engineering, Memo on Steve Jobs' Visit and a Combined Mission with Apple 1984 (Box 3)
      - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI), James Jacobs, Practitioners' Academy Pre-Proposal 1986 (Box 3)
      - Institute for Social Research (ISR) Studies 1983 (Box 3)
      - Institute of Science and Technology (IST), Employment Transition Program, Statements, Directory 1984, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Industrial Development Division (IDD)/Industrial Linkages 1985 (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw Community College
      - Administrative Positions and Employee Review Manual 1984 (Box 3)
      - Handbook, "Michigan's Community Colleges," 1985 (Box 3)
- State Government
  In the State Government series, 1983-1986 (0.6 linear ft.), additional MCCA materials are included here to represent the change in reporting relationship after responsibility for the ED&JT Network was transferred from the MCC Presidents' Committee to the Director of the MCCA, a state-supported administrative unit. This series also includes records from Bach's work with the Michigan Tax Information Council (MTIC), including examples of the "Tax Talk" Newsletter she edited.
  - Michigan Community Colleges Association (MCCA)